A Guide to the Dowell J. Howard Papers 1913-1957
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Dowell J. Howard Papers 1913-1957
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11084
There are 600 items in this collection (5 Hollinger boxes).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the Library by Marianna H. Parrish, Vienna, Virginia, on March 17, 1993, without restrictions.This collection was given to the Library by Marianna H. Parrish, Vienna, Virginia, on March 17, 1993.
Biographical/Historical Information
Dr. Dowell J. Howard (1897-1957), Virginia State Superintendent of Public Instruction (1949-1957), was born at Brookeville, Maryland, on August 11, 1897, to Henry and Mary Florence (Jones) Howard and was educated at Maryland State College (now University of Maryland) receiving his B.S. in 1917, and M.A. in 1926; He was also a student at the Virginia Polytechnic Institute in 1926. Howard began his teaching career in vocational agriculture in 1919 at Boyce, Virginia, and served as district supervisor of agricultural education for Northern Virginia, 1925-1935, until promoted to assistant state supervisor of agricultural education in 1935 and state supervisor in 1942. He then worked for the Virginia State Department of Education as assistant state superintendent of public instruction from 1946-1949, acting state superintendent, 1949-1950, and state superintendent from 1950-1957. For a complete biographical sketch, consult Who Was Who in America, Volume 3, 1951-1960, pp. 420-421.
Scope and Content Information
The Dowell J. Howard papers consist chiefly of Howard's speeches and statements to service clubs, teacher's groups, professional educators, various conferences and workshops, building dedications, high school and college commencements, educational and social commissions, and other organizations. Also present are newsclippings, personal correspondence, Howard's educational records, papers pertaining to Howard's election as district governor in the Rotary International, vita sheets, and miscellaneous materials.
His correspondence files contain letters from the following: J. Lindsay Almond (1953 Nov 11; 1954 Feb 3; 1955 Feb 9); John S. Battle (1950 May 12; 1955 Feb 14); Harry F. Byrd, Sr. (1941 Nov 24; 1944 Jul 17); Harry F. Byrd, Jr. (1949 May 26; 1950 May 15; 1952 Jun 27); Virginius Dabney (1954 Dec 16); Colgate W. Darden, Jr. (1950 May 15); George P. Freeman (1949 Sep 1); Albertis Sydney Harrison, Jr. (1950 May 16); Edward R. Johnson (1946 May 9); J.W. Jones (1939 Mar 21); Dabney S. Lancaster (1949 Sep 1); W. Nelson Page (1954 Jan 8); A. Willis Robertson (1949 Jan 25; Feb 9-10); Thomas B. Stanley (1953 Aug 27; Nov 10; 1954 Feb 2 & 27; Mar 6); and William M. Tuck (1954 Feb 4). There are additional letters from various Virginia politicians which congratulate him on his appointment as State Superintendent of Public Instruction in 1950.
Contents List
- PERSONAL & MISCELLANEOUS PAPERS
  - Newclippings re: Education in Virginia 1947-1954, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Personal Papers -- Correspondence 1926-1957, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Personal Papers -- Educational Records 1913-1940 (Box 1)
  - Personal Papers -- Rotary International 1940-1941 (Box 1)
  - Personal Papers -- U.S. Civil Service Commission 1954 (Box 1)
  - Personal Papers -- Vita Sheet 1948, 1954 & n.d. (Box 1)
- SPEECH & STATEMENT FILES
  - "Adult Education" n.d. (Box 1)
  - Annual Conference of Division Superintendents -- Speeches 1947-1956 (Box 1)
  - Apprenticeship Conference, Newport News 1956 May 16 (Box 1)
  - Articles for Publication in Magazines & Newspapers 1954 & n.d. (Box 1)
  - Beth A'Habah Speech 1952 May 26 (Box 1)
  - "Better Schools Through Better Planning" n.d. (Box 1)
  - Chamber of Commerce Speeches at Berryville & Gretna 1937 & 1951 (Box 1)
  - "The Chile -- the Home's Place in the Foundation of the Child" n.d. (Box 1)
  - Commission on Juvenile Delinquency -- "The Schools and the Delinquent Child" 1955 Apr 26 (Box 1)
  - Constitutional & Statutory Provisions and State Board Regulations 1950 (Box 1)
  - Daughters of the American Revolution -- "Education for Patriotism" 1956 Feb 22 (Box 1)
  - Dedication Speeches 1953-1955 (Box 2)
  - Distributive Education Clubs 1955, n.d. (Box 2)
  - "Driver Education in Virginia's Schools" 1950-1951 (Box 2)
  - "Education A Big Program" n.d. (Box 2)
  - Elementary Education National Consultants, Chicago -- Remarks 1955 (Box 2)
  - Farm Equiptment Institute, Chicago -- "People Are Important" 1956 Sep 26 (Box 2)
  - "50 Years of Flight" Introduction 1953 (Box 2)
  - High School Commencements 1943-1956 (Box 2)
  - "The High School Program" n.d. (Box 2)
  - Home Economics Conferences 1951-1952 (Box 2)
  - Inauguration Speeches 1950-1951 (Box 2)
  - Institute of Rural Affairs -- "Youth in Today's World" 1951 Aug 3 (Box 2)
  - Introduction of Governor John S. Battle n.d. (Box 2)
  - Kiwanis Club of Ashland & West Point -- Speeches 1944, 1955 (Box 2)
  - Kiwanis Forestry Meeting, Martinsville 1955 Feb 22 (Box 2)
  - League of Virginia Counties 1949 & 1951 (Box 2)
  - Lion's Clubs at Purcellville and Unknown City 1936, 1941 (Box 2)
  - Medical College of Virginia, School of Pharmacy Convention 1954 Jan 15 (Box 2)
  - "Model General Assembly" 1953-1954 (Box 2)
  - National Beta Club Speech 1953 Apr 18 (Box 2)
  - National Guard Speech n.d. (Box 2)
  - "National Ideals and Our Influence as a World Power" n.d. (Box 2)
  - National Office Management Association, Richmond Traffic Club, & The Commonwealth Magazine-- "Publication Education: A Big Business" 1952-1954 (Box 2)
  - North Carolina Superintendent's Conference -- "The Challenge Facing Public Education in the Next Decade" 1955 Jun 28 (Box 2)
  - Optimist Club, Richmond -- "Education in our Democracy" 1953 Feb 2 (Box 2)
  - Parent-Teacher Association Speeches 1952-1955 (Box 2)
  - Planned Parenthood Organization -- "Virginia's Population in Relation to Education" 1952 (Box 2)
  - "Planning an Effective School Program" 1949 Feb 18 (Box 2)
  - "A Point of View of Education" 1945 Apr 27 (Box 2)
  - Practical Nurses Association, Richmond -- "Human Relations" 1948 Oct 14 (Box 2)
  - Principal's Conferences Speeches 1947-1953 (Box 2)
  - "Problems for Consideration" re: Superintendent's Annual Report n.d. (Box 2)
  - "A Program of Education Which Provides For Total Child Growth" n.d. (Box 2)
  - "The Public and the Public School" n.d. (Box 2)
  - "Public School Finance in Virginia" n.d. (Box 2)
  - Railway Women's Business Club 1956 Mar 15 (Box 2)
  - Resource -- Use Workshop, V.P.I., Blacksburg 1956 Jun 13 (Box 2)
  - "The Responsibilities of School Trustees (Board of Visitors)" n.d. (Box 2)
  - Richmond Forum -- Y.M.C.A. 1950 Feb 8 (Box 2)
  - Richmond Speech -- "Eastern Star Convention" 1956 May 8 (Box 2)
  - Ruritan Clubs -- Speeches 1948-1951, n.d. (Box 2)
  - (Box 2)
  - School Trustees Meeting 1949 (Box 2)
  - Secondary Principal's Conference 1956 Jun (Box 2)
  - "The Secretary and the Job" n.d. (Box 2)
  - Teacher's Meetings & Associations Speeches 1948, 1954-1955 (Box 2)
  - State Board of Education Statements 1945-1954, n.d. (Box 3)
  - State Chamber of Commerce -- Speeches & Statements (including Junior Chamber of Commerce) 1951-1954 (Box 3)
  - The State Department of Education ca. 1945-1949 (Box 3)
  - Statements Concerning Virginia's System of Public Education 1946-1953 (Box 3)
  - Staunton Speech 1956 Jan 20 (Box 3)
  - Supervisor's Conference, Hampton -- "The Place of the Supervisor and Visiting Teacher in Virginia's Education Program" 1952-1953 (Box 3)
  - University & College Commencements 1948-1953, n.d. (Box 3)
  - University of Virginia Phi Delta Kappa 1955 Apr 15 (Box 3)
  - University of Virginia School of Administration -- "The State School Dollar" [ca. 1952?] (Box 3)
  - University of Virginia Summer Conference of School Administrators -- "The Outlook in Virginia" 1951 Aug 10 (Box 3)
  - University of Virginia Workshop on Public Welfare Administration -- "State Public Education Policies & Programs Affecting the Local Welfare Dept" 1952 Aug 18-21 (Box 3)
  - VEA Joint Meeting of Dept. of Superintendents & School Boards Association -- "Some Current Educational Problems & What We Might Do About Them" 1955 Oct 26-27 (Box 3)
  - VEA Meeting -- "Planning an Effective Program of Education For Virginia's Children" 1949 Nov 3 (Box 3)
  - VEA Annual Meeting -- "What Do You Think?" 1950 Nov 1-2 (Box 3)
  - VEA Meeting -- "Lest We Forget" 1951 Oct 31 (Box 3)
  - VEA Meeting -- "The Problems, Issues, and Opportunities in Education for Economic Understanding" 1952 Aug 1 (Box 3)
  - VEA Meeting -- "Let Down Your Buckets" 1952 Oct 22 (Box 3)
  - VEA Dept. of Superintendents -- Resolutions 1952 Oct 22 (Box 3)
  - VEA First General Session -- "Let's Take a Look" 1953 Oct 28 (Box 3)
  - Virginia Academy of Science -- "Virginia's School Building Problems" 1949, 1955-1956 (Box 3)
  - Virginia Advisory Committee on Schools and Colleges 1954-1955 (Box 3)
  - "Virginia and Her Public Schools" in Virginia and the Virginia Record1954 Jun (Box 3)
  - Virginia Conference on Education 1955 (Box 3)
  - "Virginia' Public Schools Plank" n.d. (Box 3)
  - Vocational Agriculture -- Speeches 1940-1954, n.d., 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Vocational Education -- Speeches 1937-1955, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Washington, D.C. -- Panel on Referendum re: Gray Commission Plan 1956 Aug 3 (Box 4)
  - Westmoreland Woman's Club 1950-1951 (Box 4)
  - Williamsburg Speech -- "Education in a Democracy" n.d. (Box 4)
  - "Working With School Personnel and Laymen in Preparing the Public to Participate in Nine Regional Meetings of the State Board of Education" 1948-1949 (Box 4)
  - No. 1, Speeched & Statements by Dowell J. Howard 1949-1952 (Box 4)
  - No. 2, Speeched & Statements by Dowell J. Howard 1952 May-1953 Nov (Box 4)
  - No. 3, Speeched & Statements by Dowell J. Howard 1954 Jan-1955 Aug (Box 5)